<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kumar Ayush</title>
    <description>I am Kumar Ayush, an Engineering Physics sophomore at Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay. I love to cook, travel, socialize and tap into physical sciences. My mood is usually a superposition of psychopath, mad hatter, party animal and curious being and may collapse into any of these when you meet me. This is my personal homepage</description>
    <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2016 09:54:13 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2016 09:54:13 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Witcher, Game of Thrones and Predestination: Inspirations from Irish Mythology</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was home for the past one week, having a compulsory vacation enforced by my family. I spent it reading the Witcher series. To those of you who don&#39;t know about them, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrzej_Sapkowski#The_Witcher_Saga&quot;&gt;The Witcher&lt;/a&gt; is a polish fantasy series by Andrzej Sapkowski. In the opinion of many, what makes them distinctive from fantasy series like LOTR and Harry Potter are the grey shades of morality portrayed in the world. In LOTR and HP, there is a good and there is an evil and at the end of the day, the good has to triumph over evil. In Witcher, every decision taken has varying consequences for different characters; good and bad. This fascinates the eye, because of its &lt;i&gt;natural&lt;/i&gt; appeal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Game of Thrones, the popular TV series, is the second thing that comes to my mind when you think of a grey portrayal of the world. I have not read the ASOIF books, but I am an avid follower of the show and hence believe I have an idea of the major keypoints of the show. And what I&#39;ll be talking about here are the striking similarities on some of the plotlines of Witcher and Game of Thrones. Some of them are built out of fan theories I read about GoT as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Political and sexual intrigue, although since Witcher centers around one individual and his destiny, the political aspects are perhaps not as elaborate as GoT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Witcher has an elven race &lt;i&gt;Aen Sidhe&lt;/i&gt;, and GoT&#39;s white walkers are like &lt;i&gt;sidhe&lt;/i&gt; made of ice, both derived from Ao Si in Irish mythology. We also know that Children of the Forest made White Walkers so they represent &lt;i&gt;Aen Sidhe&lt;/i&gt; better, and then they have a sister race called &lt;i&gt;Aen Elle&lt;/i&gt; which looks like a representation of the Others in Irish mythology, and of WW in GoT. Witcher&#39;s &lt;i&gt;Aen Elle&lt;/i&gt; have their own version of rogue riders called the Wild Hunt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A major problem which surrounds the world as per a prophecy is the coming of a great winter; a great iceage, the Big Winter, the Big Chill, Aep Deireadh and many other names used for a long iceage. Witcher brings in a bit of science too by discussing that this will be effectively due to a change in tilt of Earth&#39;s axis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both of them have a central character who can travel through Space and Time. This is Witcher&#39;s Cirilla or Ciri, and GoT&#39;s Brandon Stark. Although, in the case of GoT, it is only fan theories which talk about a predestination. Witcher, on the other hand, is very explicit to center the story around Ciri&#39;s predestination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent long hours searching for popular Irish mythological stories so we could establish a connection. Witcher was published before ASOIF and ASOIF was published by the time Witcher was well known to the English speaking world. These are just my reflections.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2016 12:56:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/75dos/literature/pop/2016/06/18/on-irish-mytho/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/75dos/literature/pop/2016/06/18/on-irish-mytho/</guid>
        
        
        <category>75dos</category>
        
        <category>literature</category>
        
        <category>pop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Slicing Python Lists</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A lot many are familiar with Python lists and the feature of slicing, although I find the description that most tutorials not intuitive enough. Here is how it goes.&lt;br /&gt;
Let us start with defining an array of 10 elements
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = [i for i in range(10)]
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, the following I assume you&#39;re familiar with.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a[3:6]
[3, 4, 5]
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And the way people think about it is selecting elements starting with &lt;i&gt;index 3&lt;/i&gt; till and including the element with &lt;i&gt;index 6-1=5.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Do you digest that? I cannot. Why do I include the first index while not the second one? If I think in terms of indices, I have to spend my brain power in subtracting the second index by one, and I tell you I am very lazy about that. 
&lt;br /&gt;
Then there are people who say that you start with &lt;i&gt;index 3&lt;/i&gt; and choose &lt;i&gt;6-3=3&lt;/i&gt; elements there on. This does work because we see the following happening.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a[4:4]
[]
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But I do not understand that if I were inventing slicing, and I would want people to think in terms of an index and a length, why would I not just keep length as the second parameter? In this &lt;b&gt;hypothetical&lt;/b&gt; situation,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a[3:3]
[3, 4, 5]
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;DISCLAIMER: I do not claimer that this is how it went but I&#39;ll now talk about how I like to look at slicing&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a[3:]
[3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9]
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I like to say that doing this &lt;i&gt;skips&lt;/i&gt; the first &lt;i&gt;three&lt;/i&gt; elements and gives the rest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a[:6]
[0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And this picks the first &lt;i&gt;six&lt;/i&gt; elements. Simple really!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a[3:6]
[3, 4, 5]
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This just gives the &lt;i&gt;intersection&lt;/i&gt; of the two.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My two cents.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2016 02:21:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/75dos/python/programming/2016/06/03/on-splicing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/75dos/python/programming/2016/06/03/on-splicing/</guid>
        
        
        <category>75dos</category>
        
        <category>python</category>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Circle enclosing N lattice points</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know?&lt;br /&gt;For every natural number N, there exists a circle enclosing exactly N lattice points!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/26vUCSK9K5wTm5fwI/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;gif demonstrating fact&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above was posted on the Facebook group of Math n Physics Club of my institute. It triggered a discussion about the center of such a circle with one guy commenting without reason enough that it has to be an irrational point and any irrational point would do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it interesting and thought over it while taking a shower. &lt;i&gt;If&lt;/i&gt; the center is at origin, then this is impossible. If you try to enclose a point at a distance $\sqrt{d^2}$, you will find that $d^2 = x^2 + y^2$ where you don&#39;t have a unique choice of $x$ and $y$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now note that if the center is a rational point, say $(\frac{a}{b},\frac{c}{d})$, then you can scale the space by $bd$, then the center lies at $(ad,bc)$ and then a simple translation will take you to origin and our hypothesis is reduced to the above case raising a contradiction against our assumption that the center is a rational point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the center must be an irrational point. I do not know if any irrational point would do though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My two cents!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 20:01:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/75dos/misc/math/2016/05/14/n-points-in-circle/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/75dos/misc/math/2016/05/14/n-points-in-circle/</guid>
        
        
        <category>75dos</category>
        
        <category>misc</category>
        
        <category>math</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On DSLR-Description</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am in custody of the Canon EOS 700D camera owned by Krittika-Astronomy Club of IIT Bombay. I&#39;ve always been able to have the IQ level to snap a picture from the camera required at social gatherings but have never been able to make sense of all the variety of features that it brings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took an attempt to study the specifications of the camera and learn how to use it to get good pictures for specific situations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/media/75dos_dslr.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2016 23:50:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/75dos/misc/skills/2016/05/03/on-dslr/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/75dos/misc/skills/2016/05/03/on-dslr/</guid>
        
        
        <category>75dos</category>
        
        <category>misc</category>
        
        <category>skills</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Webcam Spectrograph using RPi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We made a webcam spectrograph using an optical CD as the diffraction grating as our course project for Waves, Oscillation and Optics (EP 226). As processing the camera images on a computer would be too boring, we used an RPi board with embedded camera which we happened to have. The RPi could process and transmit the data over WiFi enabling us to access the results from any computer, in principle. This made the spectrograph completely portable,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our professor suggested many possible improvements onto this which would make it a cheap product for schools. They include distancing the grating from the camera and using a good grating rather than the CD which has curved grooves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation is available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1qCOpMDIkoW5DiRjUoKt6KazmboxlhlZCXlEeynKLJM0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; drive link.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 23:42:04 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/projects/optics/rpi/2016/04/15/webcam-spectrograph/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/projects/optics/rpi/2016/04/15/webcam-spectrograph/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>optics</category>
        
        <category>rpi</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>3 body Simulation using FPGA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were supposed to make something using Terasic DE0-Nano boards equipped with Altera Cyclone IV E FPGA as a part of our course project in Digital Electronics Lab(EP 230). We went around to explore what are some things which an FPGA can do better than a CPU. Starting with High Frequency Trading and Bitcoin computation, we evolved our idea into N body simulation which we could complete for 3 body simulation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general idea is easy to grasp. Consider that you are simply calculating the vector r&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; - r&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;. This requires 3 subtractions which a simple CPU will serially do, but on an FPGA we can program three subtractors to work in parallel. The improvement in speed is challenged by a requirement of larger hardware(Flops per unit area), but hardware is cheap and time is not, thus FPGAs seek good applications in high performance computing till date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full abstract can be downloaded &lt;a href=&quot;/media/fpga_doc.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the presentation is available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1tZKQbFShL-eHozx8fI_xyVnHJPRaeSnEXDdIa1Blzi0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; drive link.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2016 00:42:04 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/projects/digital-systems/coding/computational/2016/04/14/3-body-simulation-fpga/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/projects/digital-systems/coding/computational/2016/04/14/3-body-simulation-fpga/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>digital-systems</category>
        
        <category>coding</category>
        
        <category>computational</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photometry-Techniques and Applications</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The fundamental principles and pre-requisites to astronomical photometry was introduced. We then proceeded to discuss some practical applications including a demonstration on light curve analysis at planethunters.org
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 23:04:22 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/talks/astronomy/2016/03/03/photometry/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/talks/astronomy/2016/03/03/photometry/</guid>
        
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>astronomy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MIT Scratch Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We offered a workshop on MIT Scratch followed by a 3-day contest. This is aimed to be an introduction to prgramming for the freshmen batch.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 23:04:22 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/talks/programming/2016/02/02/scratch-day/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/talks/programming/2016/02/02/scratch-day/</guid>
        
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to Positional Astronomy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This offered an introduction to spherical trigonometry and astronomical co-ordinate systems. Fundamental applications such as prediction of eclipses were mentioned.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 23:04:22 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/talks/astronomy/2016/02/02/positional-astronomy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/talks/astronomy/2016/02/02/positional-astronomy/</guid>
        
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>astronomy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Variability analysis for the globular cluster NGC 2419</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full report can be downloaded &lt;a href=&quot;/media/nius-2015.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 23:04:22 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/projects/astronomy/photometry/2016/01/15/variability-analysis-ngc-2419/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://cheekujodhpur.github.io/projects/astronomy/photometry/2016/01/15/variability-analysis-ngc-2419/</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
        <category>astronomy</category>
        
        <category>photometry</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
